- This morning.
(audience cheers)
All right, it is day two.
It's our second day together.
So thank you for bringing the energy
back into the room this morning.
We're gonna need it to sustain us
through all of the wonderful things
we have to go through together today.
I'm Jory Hadsell.
I serve as the vice chancellor
and CTO-type facilitating collaboration
between Foothill-De Anza and the state Chancellor's Office.
(audience cheering) (audience applauding)
Thank you.
So, as our technology evolves, so do our roles.
And right now I kinda feel like I'm living proof
that sometimes your job description
needs to be updated in real time.
So I'm hoping AI can help me with that.
So, again, thank you for being here.
I wanted to go over
just a couple of housekeeping items real quickly.
Please, again, pay attention to the conference app today.
If there are any changes or updates,
we'll push those out through the app.
So if you have the Cvent app,
it's your handy little guide as you go through the morning.
Also, just wanted to give a reminder
to please silence your cell phones.
And that's easy to forget to do,
that occasionally happens to me too,
so just for the benefit of everyone.
And if you need to get up and leave the auditorium,
we just appreciate you trying to leave quietly.
So thank you so much.
Before we set today's course, we do wanna pause.
Today is September 11th,
and we remember the lives that were lost
and forever changed in 2001,
in the horrific terrorist attacks.
So today we wanna remember and honor the victims,
the survivors, the first responders, and their families.
So please, help us honor
the resilience that brings us together in rooms like this,
that proves that even in the face of the deepest tragedies,
we can be resilient and united,
which is maybe more important than ever.
So I'd like to invite you to join me briefly
for a moment of silence
as we remember those who were lost on September 11th
due to the tragic events of that day.
Thank you for holding that space.
Well, we are here today
to shape what comes next, looking forward.
Day one reminded us that the future is already here.
Day two is about what we choose to do with it, right?
And who better to choose what our future is gonna look like
than all of us who are shaping the lives
of so many of our students.
We're going to look at how we align ethics,
creativity, and sustainability
so that our decisions today stand up tomorrow.
One year ago, on this stage, by the way,
we announced the Digital Center for Innovation,
Transformation and Equity.
You heard some of that from Chancellor Christian yesterday.
And since then, together,
we've gone from concept to outcomes,
piloting, testing, and scaling tools that serve students
and the colleges that serve them, all of you.
This is the story, again, of how this community of colleges
can come together and innovate.
To hear a little bit more about the incredible work
our founding partners are doing
to benefit the entire system,
I'd like to welcome to the stage
the leaders of our founding partner districts,
please give them a round of applause.
(all applauding)
(speakers speaking indistinctly)
You may recognize some of these folks.
If you don't, you'll get to hear
about some of the work that they're doing.
And we're so excited to have you on stage.
Thank you for being with us this morning.
So we'll start here with someone
who is not here in digital twin form today,
but in real life.
(all laughing)
Chancellor Lambert from-
- I am real.
(all laughing)
- Chancellor Lambert from Foothill-De Anza.
You know, Lee, last year, we were talking
about the launch of LightLeap in AI fraud detection
and some other things we're working on.
That effort has actually reached
over 80 of our colleges already.
It's been really incredible to watch that progress.
But I know you're already looking around the corner
to see what's next.
So could you talk a little bit about what you're seeing
on perhaps how's the most collaboration you see
that raise the floor on readiness and digital trust?
- Absolutely, Jory. Good morning, everybody.
- [Audience] Good morning.
- So how many seconds are there in a day?
86,000 seconds in a day.
And so according to a University of Maryland study,
I think I'm right to say it's University of Maryland,
every 39 seconds there's a cyberattack.
Now, according to some of the major corporations,
that number is probably a little too conservative.
So can you imagine, even if it was more than one attack,
every 39 seconds.
How many unfilled cyber positions are there
across the United States of America?
A conservative estimate is around 500, 600,000.
That's all up and down the cyber continuum.
But now contrast that with nurses.
How many nursing vacancies are there
across the United States of America?
Probably in the neighborhood of 200,000.
What conversation aren't we having?
Cyber reality.
We're not talking about that
in terms of how we as colleges are filling that.
So in conversations with IBM,
we need to bring forward the next level
of cybersecurity education and training programs.
I think that's gonna be an important frontier
because you can't talk AI,
you can't talk these four superpowers
that I talk about a lot,
without talking about cybersecurity.
So I think that's an important piece
we have to focus on as well as an entire system of colleges,
because we've got to address the reality
of this growing cyber problem
across our country and across the globe.
Thank you.
- Thank you so much, Chancellor Lambert.
Turning to President Jeannie Kim
from Santiago Canyon College representing Rancho Santiago
as one of the founding districts.
Again, you were also one of the earliest
along the ride with LightLeap
and working on the fraud problem,
but I know you're also working on some other things too.
Maybe you could talk a little bit
about how you're revolutionizing
your apprenticeship process.
- Yeah, so one of the pain points
that we identified early on
was that we weren't able to award the certificates
and identify the actual successful completions
of our students in the apprenticeship program
because there were a lot of substitutions
and a variety of different specialized areas.
And so what we did was we engaged
with Kiran and with LightLeap and our counseling faculty,
and we're fortunate to have an apprenticeship counselor
dedicated to working with our apprentices.
And so they've been developing a AI solution
to be able to take all of the historical data,
the current data, train the model so that that process
of awarding these degrees and certificates
is more automatic.
We're not taking the human out of the loop.
The humans will still continue to monitor
and make sure that these awards and degrees are accurate,
but we will no longer be behind
because we don't have all of the resources
or the historical knowledge.
And so that's actually a revolutionary thing for us
in terms of making sure
that we're able to do a little bit better
in relation to those auto-awarding degrees
'cause previously we were about three years behind,
and that was actually impeding then the students
in relation to their ability to complete
or have evidence of conclusion.
- I love the way you're centering students in that work
and using AI to, again, revolutionize these processes.
Chancellor Whitney Yamamura from the Coast district.
Is anyone from Coast here by the way?
(audience cheers)
(audience applauding)
It's okay. We can be interactive this morning.
(all laughing)
Go Coast. There you go.
- [Audience Member 1] Yeah.
- So Coast has been, again, a leader in the field,
in the Common Cloud Data Platform, for example,
demonstrating that turning the data plumbing work
can actually help us increase our success with our students.
Wanted to just give you a minute to talk about that work.
- Oh, that's great.
Yes, first, tip of the cap to State Chancellor Christian.
It was her idea to have a common data cloud
that's agnostic of whatever ERP you use.
So it doesn't matter if it's PeopleSoft
or it's Banner or it's Colleague, whatever you use,
being able to have a common reference
so that it's easier for us to do research across the state
and gather information, that's a big plus.
On a practical basis for the colleges,
again, in tribute to Vice Chancellor
and our Chief Technology Officer,
Rupa Saran's sitting there,
in the initial project, the proof of concept
was six colleges.
Because they were so inefficient and effective,
they added another seven.
Imagine a project where you actually exceed
your initial requirements.
And we got funding for another round.
So all of you districts out there,
we're expanding our proof of concept because it's working.
The practical reality for you,
state chancellors and presidents, superintendents,
and your CEOs, your MIS reporting,
is that you get cleaner data faster
and we save staff time.
So it actually helps your bottom line.
We think we're gonna reduce the need for a staff
by almost one full FTE.
So that's in tight budget times.
We should be easier,
we should take advantage of technology
to have cleaner, faster data.
- Thank you so much.
Turning to President Virginia Guleff from Butte College.
Thank you for being here. (audience member cheers)
- Thank you. (audience cheers)
So your turn (voice drowned by applause).
(all laughing)
And for those of you who don't know,
Virginia is also kind of a ringleader
up in the far north region.
She's very good at convening
a lot of our small rural colleges.
So we're really thrilled to have you as part of the group.
Butte is also home to the CCC Technology Center,
which is our backbone for infrastructure
for a lot of the work that our system does.
So we're excited to ask you,
how are you using AI supporting outreach
to connect students with some of their needs?
- Thank you so much, Jory.
And I just wanna qualify what ringleader means.
I think that's important at this day and age-
- That's positive by the way.
- Being in the far north. (all laughing)
I wanna share with you something.
You'll see that I have my analog notes
for what we're saying today backed up by my phone.
So this is the intersection of what we're trying to do
when we wanna reach our students.
We know that they have their iPads
and their tablets and their laptops,
but they also have a bunch of paper
that we've given them about our colleges.
And so in the far north,
we're piloting a program with a couple of other colleges,
it's called CaliBot program.
And the idea is that we will connect with Mainstay,
and we will make a commitment
to provide real-time assistance to students.
And Mainstay will do, this is where my notes come in,
will establish escalation paths,
which is important for us.
When our students ping our college for information,
we wanna know when and how and where they're doing that.
So Mainstay is gonna help us track that.
And then we're going to make connections
with students to staff.
And we know that some of our students
are happy to talk with a bot and a bot only,
but also students want to connect with a person.
And just finally, I'd like to say one of the other ways
that we can really help our students connect,
and we can help our campuses connect with this technology,
is to involve them in the development
and the selection of the technology
we'll use at our college.
So thank you.
- Thank you so much. It's exciting work.
And by the way, all of these things we're talking about,
these districts have committed
to share with the rest of the system.
That's part of the work we're doing to the Digital Center.
So as you're hearing about their work,
the idea is this can benefit all of us
in the work we're doing for all of our students statewide.
Dave Barnett, Vice Chancellor at Kern CCD.
Is anyone from Kern here?
- [Audience Member 2] No.
(Jory speaks faintly) (all laughing)
- So, Dave, Kern is doing some interesting work,
actually something a little mobile,
would you like to share with us what you've got planned?
- Yeah, sure.
So we are implementing the Dreamscape Learn mobile trailer
and we just had a call on Monday
where we expect it to be delivered next month.
So we're super excited about that milestone.
And we're excited about bringing
the immersive experience to our students,
and hopeful that that story creates an emotional connection,
and really hope students learn that material.
And the mobile piece is important for us
because we're a 25,000 square mile service area.
And so rather than just having it in one location
and making the students come to that location,
we can bring this experience to the students.
And so we're really excited about that.
- That's worth clapping for.
(all applauding)
Thank you, Dave.
Super excited to see how that progresses.
Turning to Chancellor Julianna Barnes from South Orange.
Thank you so much for being here.
I know you're heavily involved,
your faculty were doing a lot of work
in testing the Canvas AI components,
some of those before they came out.
I know you have a deep bench
centered on human-centered digital tools.
What would you like to share this morning?
- Well, first of all,
I really want the rock star bus that Kern has, so...
(all laughing)
That one.
You know, one of the things that's top of mind for me
is Community College 3.0
and what happens post-completion with our students,
which is embedded into our new strategic plan.
So quickly, 'cause I know you said
we have one or two minutes.
Quickly, I have a story with Gohar and I
where she pulled me in to go rogue yesterday.
We were headed to a workshop
that was gonna bring together industry and education
to be sure that, you know, students are getting the skills
and experiences and certifications needed
to go into the industry.
So we said, "What better way to do it
than to crash the other big convention?"
(all laughing)
I'm putting it on Gohar.
So we did, we went rogue.
(all laughing)
And we asked the employers like, "Are we doing our job,"
you know, "What do our students need?
Where are the gaps?"
And they were like all over it.
I tried to get in yesterday,
and the staff person at the door said, "You can't come in."
I was like...
Anyway, so Community College 3.0 really top of mind.
What happens with students later?
So going back to our pilot
and some of the work that we're doing with Canvas,
I know many of the colleges are doing that.
I was having discussions with some of my team members
and I think one of the ways
in which the Digital Center could help,
in partnership with the community college districts,
is wouldn't it be lovely
if we were able to use AI-powered tools combined with Canvas
to really get that information
so that students have some type of a portfolio
immediately upon graduation
that perhaps connected with LinkedIn, for example,
so that students have some type of a portfolio ready
so that when they're looking for employment post-completion
that they have that?
And so we are assisting them with that.
So that's one thing.
And then quickly, the other thing,
we're talking a lot about practices,
but also top of mind is practitioners.
And so obviously it's our practitioners
who are driving this work.
So I would love to see some type
of a really intentional coordinated effort
to better understand digital literacy
among our employees or faculty or classified professionals,
and then to understand where the gaps are,
and for there to be very intentional efforts
with what I like to say elevating hearts and minds
with regard to professional learning and development.
So two thoughts. - Absolutely.
(audience member cheers) (audience applauding)
(audience member shouts indistinctly)
Yeah, there's so much great work happening.
Chancellor Melissa Moreno
from San Mateo County Community College District.
You're doing a lot of work in leading with curriculum,
and instructional design,
and thinking about professional development.
What would you like to share?
- Thank you.
Well, first of all, I am so excited to be here.
I wanna thank the Chancellor's Office,
Chancellor Christian, Rory, Don, the whole team
because I went away yesterday
feeling super excited, and I'm like,
"Why do I feel so excited?"
Because I love to be standing on the edge
of innovation and change and the unknown,
and I think that we're all here right now.
And so I think we kinda just need to give it up
to be able to have this conversation
and for bringing this crew.
So thank you for that.
(all applauding)
At San Mateo, any San Mateo?
(audience cheering) (audience member applauds)
So what we're doing as a partner to the Digital Center
and as a partner with our industry specialists
is, you know, we wanna leverage
our instructional design expertise.
So at each of our three campuses,
Cañada College, College of San Mateo, and Skyline College,
we have centers for teaching and learning,
and we actually have a cadre of faculty
who are instructional designers.
And so we really wanna leverage that.
Because my big thing is we have to create environments
for our students to succeed,
and it's faculty who create those environments.
And so we really need to be
on the leading edge of the unknown and of change
to figure out what those classrooms environments look like
so that our students are showing up
with intrigue and curiosity.
We have to be ahead of it.
We have to be moving at the speed of innovation.
And so we're focused on professional development modules
for faculty and in the classrooms.
And I just wanna thank our faculty.
We have champion faculty here,
and we're part of the AI community of practice,
and we have faculty that are really leaning in to this work
that we are excited to be able to share statewide
and in partnership with the Digital Center.
So thank you.
- Thank you.
Yeah, we're excited that pace of innovation
and the pace of professional development
just keeps getting faster and faster, right?
So definitely excited for that.
And thank you so much.
I also wanna give a quick shout-out
to our newest founding partner,
not here with us on the stage today, but El Camino College.
Anyone from El Camino?
(audience member cheers)
All right, there we go.
(all applauding)
They're engaged with us
and working on some policies around AI and IT.
So we're looking forward
to hearing more from them very soon.
And, again, to all of our partners,
you've helped us prove what's possible this year
when we can prototype together and scale together.
This is the kinda collaboration on a grand scale
that's gonna benefit everyone like I mentioned before.
So thank you for dedicating your time and your resources
to all of us doing that important work
and for sharing that with the rest of the system.
Now since this is our first anniversary
of the Digital Center,
I thought it would be a great idea to mark it
with a one-year birthday celebration.
So if our partners could please stand?
No celebration would be complete unless we had what?
- [Audience Member 3] Cake. - Cake.
Cake, right?
Oh wait, I'm being told that actually
we have a virtual cake this year,
with the assistance of AI.
So we won't sing,
but we'll just say to a year of doing the work, thank you.
(audience cheers) (all applauding)
Thank you all for being here.
Give another hand for our founding partners.
(audience and Jory applauding)
All right, that was excellent.
Today's main stage we're going to press again
on three through lines to the conversation,
ethical guardrails and equity by design,
creative potential in human plus AI collaboration,
and climate resilience and mental health,
all that whole sphere through workforce readiness.
So I hope you are ready for day two
as much or more than day one.
We have a packed agenda.
We're gonna move briskly through that agenda, so be ready.
We're gonna kick it off together.
You excited?
- [Audience] Yeah.
(all applauding)
- So, as we get ready, I wanna bring out
a familiar face to many of you.
We wanna thank N2N Services
for being one of our sponsors for the summit today.
And here to share a little bit of information
about what's happening with N2N and the LightLeap product,
I'd like to invite out the CEO of N2N Services,
Kiran Kodithala.
Kiran?
(Jory and audience applauding)
(bright music)
- Thanks, Jory.
And congratulations on the first year birthday.
Speaking of birthdays, I just turned 50 last week.
I know you all shall say, "Oh, you don't look 50, Kiran."
(audience laughing)
I'll take it, I'll take it.
I'll take it all from everybody and have a great day.
But a lot has changed,
in addition to me getting older, with LightLeap.
We all know LightLeap as one monolithic thing
that does a couple of things
or one of the things that we talked about.
But over the last year, we've been rapidly innovating
thanks to some of the incredible collaboration
that's occurring between the California Community Colleges,
and I want to highlight a few of them.
And first one is with Polaris,
our student services platform.
We originally designed Polaris
to allow a student to get whatever help they want
as quickly as they can get,
and that was kind of the genesis
of our collaboration with Mission College
under President Awan's leadership.
President Awan reached out to us about,
and a problem with Mission CARES,
you all know it as College of Desert CARES or Coast CARES,
or whatever you are, like with the basic needs,
EOPS and others.
She wanted to solve the problem
of getting the students the help they need using AI.
Let's hear from President Awan.
- [Awan] We have all of our students
complete one application,
and we triage those applications and those students
to help them figure out what they qualify for.
This process was very, very labor intensive
and it was taking up a lot of manpower,
a lot of time auditing spreadsheets
and trying to reconcile different systems.
And so with reaching out to LightLeap AI,
they were able to help us really start to automate systems,
analyze processes, and use AI and AI agents-
- Well, technical glitch.
Without technical glitch,
there is no technical presentation, I guess.
(audience laughs)
The second part is Prism.
We originally started Prism
as a document ingestion platform
because Ivy Tech was dealing
with hundreds of thousands of transcripts and documents
from high school students
and they wanted a way to read transcripts
at a speed of light
so that they not only read the transcript,
but articulate them quickly.
However, we never thought that this technology we created
to massively increase online learning
can help with offline learning until I met Clint Cowden.
Clint Cowden, we met at a CSSO conference
while he was eating lunch somewhere,
and he presented this unique problem
of connecting AI with offline learning
for his Rising Scholars Program.
Let's hear from Clint directly.
- [Clint] Previous to AI, what we were doing,
especially for something like
when we wanted to get a student accepted to our our college,
we would actually mail them a paper application.
The student would receive that from their pesky,
or a local person at the institution
that would provide them that.
They would fill out that information.
That would then get mailed to Palo Verde College.
Really, truth, honestly, Palo Verde College
is very happy to be using LightLeap AI.
It has really helped our college.
So LightLeap AI and Palo Verde College
is really excited to continue to move forward.
- So how does all this happen, right?
How does the same company that is serving,
processing hundreds of gigabytes of data to identify fraud
is also doing document ingestion,
is also doing student services connection?
It's all because of our Atlas platform.
Our Atlas platform is a data modeling system
that can take data from any source
and convert it to actionable intelligence,
and that's one of the things
that we are incredibly excited about.
And all of this is useless if it is just a bunch of scripts
and functions and dashboards.
So we tied it all together
with a conversational operating system called Ether,
which is a chatbot operating system
that connects any system, student information system,
learning management system, AI agents, or any other systems.
So Gary Moser from Kern came up with this interesting idea
of what if we can connect advisors
to student services needs
so that students can get exactly the right courses
as a result of guided pathways?
So let's hear from Gary directly.
- [Gary] Many of our students have spent time
going through and selecting courses
that may not directly apply to the program
or degree they're seeking.
And we get concerned that the students
are taking an awful long time in the community college
and also taking extra courses
that are not necessarily required,
take that information,
and bounce it against their record of program of study
and find out where their gaps were,
whether they took courses or not,
whether they're missing courses.
And then AI would calculate that information
and recommend, using N2N as a partner,
we think we can scale this very well,
not only for Banner schools,
but for Colleague schools, PeopleSoft.
I don't think it's really gonna matter,
because the capability that we have
and partnership that we've built with N2N to be successful
is gonna lend itself to years.
- I think I'm missing one other platform
we all are familiar with, right?
Our fraud elimination platform.
How many of you here are using
our fraud elimination platform?
Right?
So right now that has been a success story in itself.
When we started this just last year,
speaking of first year birthday,
I was here talking to Futures Summit last year
where we had two districts using the platform
and we processed close to 300,000 applications.
And now, after about a year,
we processed close to three million applications.
And as a result,
we caught close to 850,000 fraudulent factors.
Great round of applause (voice drowned by applause).
(audience applauding)
Speaking of digital area of innovation
or LightLeap innovation or Lightspeed,
in my lifetime of 37 years, that's how old I am,
in higher education terms,
I've never seen anything go this fast, not even in general.
And it's not just because of one thing,
it's not just because of we have an incredible team
with N2N called LightLeap AI team,
but we also have incredible collaboration
with leaders like Jory, Dr. Lambert,
Rupa from Coast, Gary, and Napa Valley, Cerritos,
and every single one of you
deciding to implement fraud detection
to solve this systemic problem.
And I'm happy to report that,
I feel that with the incredible collaboration we have,
not just with LightLeap AI team and the Chancellor's Office,
but also with the tech center,
I feel that the fraudsters are on retreat,
at least from California.
What we have seen is, with San Bernardino,
there's almost a 30% to 7% drop in fraud.
And some institutions, believe it or not,
was dealing with over 74% fraud.
That means that one out of four three applications,
three or four applications were fraudulent.
And we are able to report
that the fraudsters are on the retreat.
And, again, it's only because
of the incredible collaboration underway
between each of the districts, each of the colleges,
and the Chancellor's Office,
and most importantly tech center as well.
And I can go on and on about Orion,
but we don't have that much time.
I wanna end with this slide
because, you know, speaking of birthdays,
N2N has turned 15 this year.
I started N2N on December 23rd, 2010,
and we're celebrating our 15th year anniversary
in Quantum Leap.
And you can see the information on the URL.
However, after talking so much to Dr. Kim,
after listening to Chancellor Sonya Christian,
and Dr. Lambert talked about how important it is
to be a internship-friendly state, which you are,
I want to announce, you know, a incubator
that we're launching only for community college students
where we will receive applications
from community college students
that want to build an AI product.
And what we will do, as part of this incubator,
is we'll set aside at least $100,000 in cash prices
because, to build on Chancellor Christian's vision
on providing internships for everybody,
but in addition we'll give them CMO services,
chief marketing officer services, CTO Services,
chief financial officer Services.
Because anybody can have an idea,
but it is so hard to think about
how to take that idea and make it real.
So check out Quantum Leap and check out the information.
And thank you so much for your time.
Incredibly appreciate all the support
and help we are getting from all of you.
Thank you so much.
(audience cheers) (audience applauding)
- Well, good morning, everyone.
- [Audience] Good morning.
- Yeah, it's me again, I know.
(audience laughing)
He's back, right? Thank you.
So we have a special line of speakers for you today,
beginning with this morning's fireside chat
and our final keynote speaker,
Henk Rogers of Tetris, acclaimed,
and physical visionary philanthropist
of the Blue Planet Alliance.
As we gather here this morning,
we're not just talking about the future.
As Chancellor Christian mentioned,
we're actively creating it.
Vision 2030 is our roadmap for this journey.
Centering equity, climate action,
and the transformative potential of artificial intelligence
in all the work that we do.
This isn't just policy on paper,
it's our commitment to 2.1 million students
who walk through our doors,
trusting us to prepare them for a world that's changing
at unprecedented speed.
And while these imperatives require us
to harness technological innovation,
we must do so with unwavering commitment to justice.
Our Board of Governors has given us a clear mandate
to address these challenges
on behalf of the citizens of California.
As we stand at the crossroads of technological advancement,
we must examine artificial intelligence
through an intersectional lens
that considers both its extraordinary potential
and its profound risk.
AI offers unprecedented opportunities
to close equity and opportunity gaps,
yet we cannot ignore its potential
for devastating socioeconomic impacts
on local communities, women and the families they care for,
and the Global South,
particularly as the race for natural resources
to fuel AI infrastructure accelerates climate change
and further marginalizes vulnerable populations.
California's Community Colleges
have the unique power and responsibility
to tackle the state's and nation's greatest challenges.
And as the nation's largest higher education system,
we are positioned to drive equitable solutions
precisely because of the diversity of our students
and our staff who reflect the larger global community,
giving us the insights
that other institutions simply cannot match.
So today, we have the honor
of hearing from two pioneering women
whose scholarship and leadership
are reshaping how we understand technology, power,
and justice in education.
Their voices are essential
as we work to build more equitable futures
for our students and communities.
Returning to Futures Summit 2025,
we are pleased to have Dr. Safiya Noble,
UCLA Professor, Director, hello?
(audience laughing)
Safiya?
No, not yet. Not yet.
I know, no, I'll have you come out later, okay.
(audience continues laughing)
UCLA professor, director of UCLA's
Center on Race and Digital Justice,
co-founder of the Minderoo Initiative
on Tech and Power at UCLA,
and author of the groundbreaking book
"Algorithms of Oppression," 2018,
which exposed how search engines
systematically misrepresented women of color
and perpetuated systemic inequalities.
Her work has become even more urgent
as we grapple with large language models
trained on public internet data
that can amplify and scale these very biases.
She'll be in conversation with author Karen Hao,
one of the foremost tech journalists,
covering AI with pieces in The Atlantic,
a leader of the Pulitzer AI series,
and whose recent and influential book "Empires of AI:
The Dreams and Nightmares in Sam Altman's OpenAI,"
provides a comprehensive examination
of how artificial intelligence shapes power structures,
reinforces existing inequalities and impacts social justice.
Hao's analysis extends to AI's devastating climate impact,
revealing how the technology's massive energy demands
and resource extraction
further entrench global inequalities.
Now, as community college leaders
serving students who have historically
been underrepresented in higher education
and often marginalized by technological systems,
we have a responsibility
to embrace technological innovation.
Even as we interrogate the use and impact of these tools,
it's our responsibility to provide the type of education
and skill sets that will allow our learners
to also interrogate those tools.
This conversation between these two influential thinkers
offers us critical perspectives on ensuring
our technological choices advance equity
rather than perpetuate harm.
Their leadership reminds us
that the voices guiding our digital future
must reflect the diversity of the communities we serve.
So with that, please give an enthusiastic welcome
to my dear friend Dr. Safiya Noble and Karen Hao
for what will undoubtedly be an illuminating
and necessary dialogue.
(audience cheers) (audience applauding)
(bright music)
- Oh my goodness, it's so great to be back with you
and to see you.
And I sent greetings from UCLA,
you know, that I always try to remind you
that the very best students that I've ever had at UCLA
come from the community colleges in California.
(audience cheering) (all applauding)
I'm so honored to be here with you.
I am absolutely trying to hold myself together
because I am the number one fangirl of Karen Hao.
And I cannot believe that I get to be up here
on this stage with you.
- I am the fangirl of Safiya, so...
- Don't even try it.
Don't even try it.
I brought a whole, like just pages and pages,
but really I just wanna do like this.
(Karen and audience laughing)
Ain't that sweet?
(all laughing)
Karen, you are, well, first of all,
I don't know if everyone here realizes
that the fact that we are even having conversations
on this stage today, in 2025,
about the harms of technology on society
is really because a group of women,
scholars and journalists, dating back to,
I don't know, a long time ago,
more than a decade, a decade and a half at least,
started writing and studying
and looking at the dark side of tech,
and Silicon Valley, where we sit today.
And you were one of those people.
So I just wanna give you your flowers
because I've been watching and reading your work
since, really, for a long time.
I feel like the longer I say, the older we seem,
so I'm trying to like, you know, walk a fine line here.
But you have been one of those voices in our world
that has helped us understand,
in a very easy to digest, you know, gut-punching way,
that what we think we know about technology in society
isn't exactly the truth and there's a lot more to see here.
So we're gonna get into talking about that
with your book, "Empire of AI,"
which, I have to say, as a person who also
had a title of a book like "Algorithms of Oppression,"
I fully appreciated "Empire of AI."
I really saw what you did there.
- Dr. Noble's work is literally why I do
so much of the work that I do.
Like, her understanding her research
and what she wrote about in "Algorithms of Oppression,"
like fundamentally changed my understanding of technology
and how I should be directing my focus
as a technology journalist.
So in terms of talking about women scholars
and intellectuals that really shaped this space,
I mean, I literally could not do the work that I did
without standing on your shoulders.
- Wow, that's very kind of you to say.
So we're just gonna-
(audience cheering) (voice drowned by applause)
Be in a moment with this.
But we're also gonna get into your book.
And before we do that, I wonder if you could help everybody
who doesn't know your background to understand.
I mean, I love the fact that you are a former engineer,
turned journalist.
And I think that's really important for the audience
to kinda get a sense of your background,
because a lot of times they'll say about someone like me,
"Well, you're a sociologist,"
you know, "You're not an engineer.
You don't fully understand,"
even though I do have a PhD in information science,
and I learned early that I hate to program,
that doesn't mean that if you are not a programmer
that you can't have something to say.
But I really think it's important
this background in engineering.
And so tell us about kind of how you got on this path.
- Yeah, so I very much never thought
that I would be a journalist.
I went and studied mechanical engineering at MIT,
in undergrad, thinking that I would join the tech industry
and that would be my career.
And so I graduated college, I moved to San Francisco,
I joined a startup in the Valley.
And very quickly, I'd like to say,
I received an education on what Silicon Valley
is actually about and that I discovered
the model of innovation that was really
being driven in this geography
was producing profitable technologies
but not technologies that benefit society.
And increasingly,
because I joined the tech industry in 2015,
increasingly we were starting to realize
that not only were they not necessarily benefiting society,
but in fact, in many ways, harming society.
This was right as Trump 1.0 was about to happen,
Cambridge Analytica revelations were about to happen.
And it really made me confront my initial assumption
about what I could actually do
working in the tech industry.
I was really interested in environmental issues at the time
and I thought that maybe there would be a place
for me developing climate technologies.
And it dawned on me in that year that I was in tech
that this is not the place where I get to work
on these long-term challenging problems
that are trying to grapple with the challenges that we face
as a human race.
Because, like, things like climate are just not profitable.
Things like trying to overcome equity issues,
or social justice issues, that's not profitable.
And so I had a little bit of a crisis moment
where I didn't really know what to do with myself.
And I sort of naively thought,
"Well, I've always really liked writing.
And I went into technology
because I thought this would be my tool for social change,
and maybe I just need to switch the tool,
from tech to writing, and writing for social change."
(audience member cheers) (audience applauding)
(voice drowned by applause)
- You know, I think about this latest work, "Empire of AI,"
and, you know, as you were talking about
wanting to use the technology to solve so many problems,
what we actually know and both write about
is that the real profit is in exploiting
the most vulnerable among us
and the vulnerabilities of our humanity.
Whether it's our vulnerabilities
to behavioral manipulation
or to exploiting our racism or sexism
or kind of the class politics.
Obviously social media is playing a huge role
in illuminating how profitable it can be
to exploit human beings.
Not just in terms of like our behavior
and how we speak to each other and how we move politically,
but also the entire supply chain
of exploitation that happens
in order to make these technologies available.
So I just wanna get right into it.
I mean, in the book,
you know, you covered this arc from kind of Sam Altman,
the personality, which, quite frankly, I,
he gets enough airtime.
So we don't have to talk about him per se,
but I do think he represents
a type of propagandist for the tech industry
and its promises while kind of obfuscating
these other dimensions of exploitation.
So what were the things that you felt
like were most important you wanted people to understand
as you were writing this book?
- Part of the reason I started working on this book,
so I've been covering AI since 2017, 2018
and I had been tracking OpenAI
specifically as a company since 2019.
And when ChatGPT came out
and suddenly the world was talking about AI,
I was honestly a little bit disappointed
because I felt like the conversation had,
there was like amnesia, everything reset,
all of the work that people
within our community of AI accountability
have been doing for years at that point,
talking about the challenges and harms of AI,
had kind of been erased and rewritten
to only have narratives
that Silicon Valley was trying to install
into the public understanding of this technology,
that it's just going to be beneficial,
it's just gonna bring the future.
And Altman was the embodiment of that.
And he was like such a good prophet for the moment
in that he seemed very different from Mark Zuckerberg.
You know, he was coming onto stages in front of congress,
in front of conferences like this
being the kind of aw-shucks guy like,
"I didn't intentionally become
the most powerful man in the world, whoopsies.
I didn't want this role.
And this technology that I'm building
is totally different from social media.
And we're not gonna repeat those mistakes.
We're like right side by side with you.
We're gonna walk you gently into the future."
And yeah, I was really frustrated
'cause I was like, "Actually, Altman is,"
he's such a product to Silicon Valley,
and AI is exactly like social media,
that it's an extension of all the ideologies
that Silicon Valley has festered for a long time.
The way that Silicon Valley builds AI
could not exist without the surveillance capitalism
that happened during the social media era.
The accumulation of all of our personal data
that was then used to train these AI models,
it could not exist without the fact
that we have sort of been lulled
into this sense that technology just,
we just have to lay down and accept it.
Like, we just have to, if we don't use these tools,
then we're going to somehow get lost in this future
and be ill-prepared.
And so that's what I ultimately wanted
to explore in the book, is to show that,
like, this is the same thing.
We've seen this story before.
We've seen Altman as a character before.
And even though OpenAI talks about it being a nonprofit,
it's also nearing a $500 billion valuation.
And we should recognize that this is not a beneficial,
you know, like mission-driven corporation
that doesn't care about our pocketbooks
and kind of just wants to bring everyone
into a kumbaya circle.
So yeah, I just wanted to tell that whole story
as well as then use it as a way
to help people understand,
the history of AI as a technology as well
so that people could feel fully equipped
to then develop a position
on how they wanna engage with this technology
and how to make sure that, ultimately,
AI serves them rather than them being served up to AI.
- Yeah, I really-
(Safiya and audience applauding)
(audience member cheers)
I remember when the Google book
digitization project was underway
and all of the academic university librarians
and all of the colleges and universities were like,
"This is gonna transform education and knowledge.
All knowledge will be open and free.
This is like kind of straight out of the Google,
you know, marketing campaign."
And then, you know, midway through that,
after they had digitized millions of volumes of books,
then there was an about-face
because of people like you,
people who were writing critically about that project,
Siva Vaidhyanathan wrote "The Googlization of Everything:
And Why We Should Worry."
People started saying like, "Well, wait a minute.
What does it mean to put all the world's knowledge
into the hands of private companies,
who then are gonna do whatever they want?"
And of course we were thinking back then,
I was thinking, "Oh, this is to train AI models," right?
And so even though we were years away from Gemini obviously.
And librarians and educators had an about-face
because they realized, "Wait a minute.
As we transfer public knowledge
into these privately held systems,
are we putting ourselves out of business?
Are we devaluing the endeavor of human knowledge creation?
Like, what are we doing here?"
And that project slowed down.
And I wonder what your speculation is
based on what you know.
I mean, obviously we've just had this anthropic lawsuit
where authors have won on copyright infringement.
You mentioned the normalization
of the kind of surveillance state
or the normalization of just all of our data
at all times being collected to train models,
even to the extent of synthetic data
now being generated to train models.
What do you think is the position might be of educators
about large language models
given what we know about what we learned from Search?
- Yeah, I think maybe the first way
that I can answer that is just to lay out
exactly what scale of data we're talking about
in terms of what is required to train the types of AI models
that these companies are developing.
And I keep specifying like the type of AI
that Silicon Valley's developing
because there's a whole landscape
of different types of AI tools that all look very different,
work very different, use different levels of data.
But specifically when we talk about ChatGPT, Gemini,
these large language model chatbot systems,
I like to use the example of Meta
because it was both a social media era company
and now is trying to enter into the AI era.
And as a social media era company,
it accumulated four billion user accounts
worth of data, right?
And literally when Meta decided
that they wanted to enter this current generative AI race,
they realized that that four billion
user accounts worth of data was not even table stakes
for them to train AI models that would be competitive
and beat out Google or OpenAI.
And so The New York Times, at the time,
reported that they were having internal conversations
in Meta about whether they should buy up Simon & Schuster,
whether they should keep scraping the entire web
again and again and again,
whether they should ultimately create
more ways of engaging users
so that users leave more and more trails of data
for them to harvest.
And it's really crazy to think about that,
like, we're talking about a fundamentally
different order of magnitude here of data
that is required to actually sustain these systems
and push the bounds of the capabilities of these systems.
And so the thing that I worry about a lot
is that these companies, they are running out of data.
They talk all the time about
how they've exhausted their data options,
and it is an existential crisis,
and they need to find ways of opening up new data streams.
They have tried doing this through synthetic data
by developing, by basically taking AI models,
existing AI models, and trying to generate that data.
But at the end of the day, research has consistently showed
that this synthetic data is just not as fresh as human data.
And so what they talk about,
and I report it in my book, within OpenAI, for example,
they talk about how they really need to cultivate
as much trust with the public as possible
so that the public will continue to give them data.
Because if they do not,
that will be existential to their business.
They talk about how they need to enter different industries
and to cultivate relationships with those industries
so that they can get access to that data.
And so what I worry about is these companies
are coming to court, universities, colleges,
the education sector at a time
when this sector is under constant threat,
and they're presenting themselves as a solution
to that threat when in fact they're exploiting
the vulnerability of this sector
during the time when it is under attack,
and using that to then create these partnerships
that lock them into a new data stream.
- Yeah, I (voice drowned by applause).
(audience applauding)
I guess you get a feel for how we feel.
(Karen and audience laughing)
It's happening right now.
Just in case we're not clear, we're gonna keep it going.
(audience member cheers) (audience applauding)
So you're absolutely right.
One of the things I think about,
you know, I'm a native California,
and I grew up in Fresno and the Bay Area,
I live in LA now.
And I think of California,
and especially this community here that we're with,
this is the largest community college system in the country,
educates 25% of community college students
in the entire United States.
Millions of people.
And so your last comment really hits home
because I think about the ways in which we've had
the most robust university system in the world,
in the community colleges, the California State University
and the University of California here.
We're right in the same state as Silicon Valley,
and you would think that our schools in California,
K through higher ed, would be the most well-resourced,
the most spectacular because of the Valley.
But instead what we have is a suite of companies
that don't pay taxes, that offshore their profits,
that don't reinvest, and then come back,
as you said, harvest our students, faculty and staff.
I mean, obviously I'm no fun at a dinner party
because this is what I wanna talk about.
Do you even wanna talk about this?
But (voice drowned by background noise),
(audience cheering) (audience applauding)
how can we, like, use this time
to help this community understand
that these deals and deal makers,
as they walk into our college campuses
and into our schools, really are part of a project
that is creating the conditions of our own demise
by not supporting the system
and then taking the community right at the top?
- Yeah, I mean, what you were saying
about how these companies don't pay taxes,
and they've just gotten wealthier
and wealthier and wealthier,
and like public institutions in California
feel like they've gotten weaker and weaker over time.
I mean, that's just evidence number one
of what the end game of these companies actually are.
They don't actually have an interest
in fortifying institutions, fortifying democracy,
and making sure that they lift all boats, right?
Like, that's why the inequality gap
has just gotten higher and higher and higher.
And you can just see, within San Francisco specifically,
how the wealth inequality, the rampant homelessness,
like these are all manifestations
of the way that the tech industry operates.
And that should be your cue to questioning everything
that they ever said to you,
all the promises that they ever make.
Because at the end of the day,
what I write about in my book
is that like we can't even think of these companies anymore
as just businesses that are providing products and services,
we have to think of them now as new forms of empire.
Because when you take a step back
and think about the degree of economic
and political power they have consolidated,
there is no nation state on this earth anymore
that can hold them accountable.
You could argue that maybe there was a time
when the US federal government could play that role,
but of course that is not going to happen anymore.
The Trump administration has demonstrated
that they have absolutely no interest
in holding these companies accountable
and, in fact, have every interest
of continuing to help them undermine public institutions,
undermine universities, undermine democracy,
and help them strike deals in places like the Middle East
and other places so that they can install
their infrastructure everywhere around the world,
and the Trump administration's project
of trying to expand the American empire.
Like, I'm not an educator, so all of you are-
(Safiya speaks indistinctly)
You are all experts in, you know, your work
and what you're seeing are the challenges of your sector.
But I am a journalist.
And what I always say to journalists,
and I do think that educators
and journalists work hand in hand,
like media organizations are also facing this challenge
of like, "Do we partner with these companies?
Do we give them all of our data,
all of the work that we've put into writing articles
and producing this well-reported documentation of history?"
And what I say to them is you have to recognize
that when you're trying to enter
these partnerships to gain access,
like gain a seat at the table,
you are actually bargaining with an industry
that does not fundamentally care
if you exist in the future.
They don't care if there are journalists in the future.
They don't care if there are human educators in the future.
I mean, they talk all the time
about how ultimately one of the promises of AI
is to replace human educators.
- That's right. - Right?
To give everyone an AI tutor.
And so there's no ability to actually have a conversation
with someone that does not care
and even does not want you to exist.
- Yeah, I mean, I have to say that,
you know, the recent study that came out of,
I think it was in MIT Tech Review,
where some of your best work is as well,
around the Fortune 500 companies rejecting chatbots now.
They've had their run, and they're like,
"Actually these are not helping us with our productivity.
In fact, we've had to invest 30% more in our labor costs
because there's so many mistakes
that are coming out of large language models
that are undermining our profitability that we're not sold."
And, you know, I always think
like this isn't the first time
when chatbots created for, I don't know, American Airlines,
and then they're like, "No, not working for us.
But you know what? You could go sell it to UCLA.
They definitely should take it."
You know what I'm saying?
Like, it's definitely good enough for them.
So I think about this kind of these products
and companies in search of markets,
and I think that you really covered that so well.
- Yeah, I mean, one of the things that,
obviously I have a lot of beef with Silicon Valley. (laughs)
But one of them is, you know,
when I was studying engineering,
we always learned that you first figure out
the challenge and scope it,
and then you figure out what kind of technology
do you build to tackle that challenge.
Because at the end of the day,
technology is meant to improve our lives.
And in the last decade plus, for Silicon Valley,
that ethos around engineering solutions to existing problems
has gone out the window,
and they advance technology for technology's sake.
And then you run into an issue
where you don't have product market fit,
but they've already poured hundreds of billions,
trillions of dollars into producing this technology.
So now they have to seek that business,
they have to figure out
where they're going to get that revenue from.
And the information just reported last week
that OpenAI originally projected
that they would roughly have a $35 billion cash burn,
and they accidentally underprojected by $80 billion.
So they now have updated their projections
saying that they're gonna have a $115 billion cash burn
in the next three years.
So they are $115 billion in the hole.
And where do you think they're going to go find that money?
Anywhere.
Anyone that will give them money
they're going to seek business with.
And they're going to tell you,
I mean, the other beef I have
is they are ultimately selling a vision of AI
that I call the everything machine.
They're coming to everyone saying,
"This AI, artificial general intelligence, AGI,
is going to cure cancer,
it's gonna solve climate change,
it's going to eradicate poverty,
it's going to fix all of our educational problems."
And throughout history,
we have always seen time and time again
that when someone gives you a potion
that's going to fix all of your problems,
they're probably charlatans.
And this is what Silicon Valley is doing.
(audience applauding) (audience member cheers)
And it's because they need that solution
to be in everything machine
so that they can fill that $150 billion hole.
- Yeah, absolutely.
And I think we have to remember
that they're not gonna get the money out of us,
'cause we don't have any money.
(audience laughs)
But we have the data, and our students have the data.
And I think about this, you know, all the time.
I remember when I was, a long time ago,
when Turnitin became the big hot thing.
And I remember, my friends and I in grad school,
we wouldn't use Turnitin.
We wouldn't let any of our students use it,
even though the university wanted us to do that,
check for plagiarism.
We're like, "What if we taught our students
that cheating only hurt themselves," you know?
Like, what if we actually approached it that way?
Because, you know, the papers
that a student writes when they're 18 or 25 or 40
to their instructor is, you know, it's personal.
It's full of a lot of half-baked ideas sometimes,
it's experimental, it's ideation.
It's not probably a thing you want
in a searchable database later on
when they're going for a job
that an employer can pull up and find,
and say like, "Oh, what were you thinking when you were 18?
And now we're gonna use that against you,"
or, "How do we build a data profile about you
based on all your past research papers," right?
I mean, there's like a lot of practical, ethical reasons
why we would not wanna put students' ideas
or faculties' intellectual property
or all of, you know, staff decisions into these systems
only to have them used as a type of predictive analytic
about people for the future.
And I know you have a lot of thoughts about what that means.
I mean, our field, we write about the harms
of predictive analytics
constantly predicting the past into the future.
I really wanna hear your take on that.
- Yeah, I mean, a lot of the entire premise of AI,
I mean, is you are training on data that existed
and then using that to predict the potentials of people,
what they are allowed to be in the future.
And of course, if you're only looking at past data,
then you're constraining the possibilities
of the future to look exactly like the past,
if not a worse version of the past.
We've now seen an abundance of research
to show that when training AI models on historical data,
that it actually exacerbates the fault lines
in that historical data and projects it
and amplifies it in the future.
And that's sort of antithetical
to the entire project of education, isn't it?
Like, we engage in education
so that we can have a fundamentally different future
than the mistakes that we've made in the past.
And so, absolutely, I-
(audience applauding)
I think that
our willingness to believe
that somehow a technology that works in this way
will fortify that project of education is,
yeah, it's really concerning
because ultimately that is not what these tools are about,
especially the way that Silicon Valley designs them.
- Yeah, I think about,
you know, you said, tell my students
the reason why
3 shirts for 20 bucks at the Gap
feels so good, like such a great deal,
is because it costs $100,000 to get a degree.
Like, the instinct for like the wanting
the easy thing that looks amazing
without any understanding of the cost
that goes into 3 shirts for 20 bucks,
3 sweaters for 20 bucks
sits in the context of what we're losing,
of what it feels further and further out of reach
in our democracy.
And I love the part, and by loved, I mean I wept,
the part of your book where you talk about
who pays the price in the Global South.
And I think that, you know, for Americans,
sometimes it's really hard to understand
because they've never been to Paraguay,
they've never been to Chile, they don't really understand.
But I think it's important
for us to talk about the Kenyan data workers
and the water and environmental costs.
- Yeah, so part of my book,
I wanted to tell the inside story of OpenAI,
but I really did not want to just stay within the Valley.
Because if you tell the story of AI, or any technology,
by only staying in one place where it actually works,
you are not going to get a clear picture
of the actual fallout that can happen globally,
especially for marginalized and vulnerable populations.
So I traveled a lot for the book.
I went to Kenya, I drew upon reporting from South Africa,
I went to Chile, I went to Hawaii, Colombia
to really understand how these communities at the margins
are actually experiencing this technology revolution
that's supposed to bring this into the future.
And so in Kenya, I met with workers
who had been contracted by OpenAI
to support the development
of what ultimately became ChatGPT.
And what OpenAI was asking these workers to do
was help them build a content moderation filter
that would sorta staple onto the models
that they were developing, the large language models,
and ensure that when users actually talk
with this text generation system that can generate anything,
that it doesn't end up generating racist, toxic hate speech
because then it would not be a commercial success.
And so for the Kenyan workers,
what that meant was they had to wade through
reams and reams of the worst content on the internet,
as well as AI-generated content
where OpenAI was prompting its own AI models
to imagine the worst possible content you could find
on the internet.
And then they had to label and put these pieces of text
into a detailed taxonomy that OpenAI provided them.
Is this hate speech? Is this violent speech?
Is this sexual content?
Is this sexual content that involves abuse
and abuse of children?
So they were asking them to do these detailed evaluations
of how bad is this content and what kind of badness is it
so that when they trained this content moderation filter,
that filter would then be able to distinguish
between these things and block it out of ChatGPT.
These workers ended up having
the same exact psychological impacts
that content moderators of the social media era had.
They ended up deeply traumatized.
They ended up with completely altered personalities.
Many of them were extroverted and warm and social
before they started the project,
and then after became extremely socially anxious,
very isolated.
And I talk about this one man, Mophat Okinyi,
who was part of this group of Kenyan workers
that was on the sexual content team for OpenAI.
And as his personality did a complete 180,
he didn't know how to explain this to his wife
and to his stepdaughter
because he didn't know how to tell them,
"My job involves reading sex content all day."
That didn't sound like a real job.
ChatGPT hadn't come out yet.
So there's like not even a conception of like,
"Why would you be doing that?
That sounds very shameful."
And so as his wife became more and more confused,
she also became less and less certain about their marriage.
And so one day she asks him, "Can we get fish for dinner?"
He goes out to the store, buys three fish,
one for him, one for her, one for the stepdaughter.
And by the time he comes back,
all of their bags have been packed and they've left.
And his wife says, texts him and says,
"I don't know the man you've become anymore.
We're not coming back."
- Yeah, I remember Sarah Roberts's book,
"Behind the Screen," about content moderation,
commercial content moderation workers.
So many thousands and thousands of stories
of people whose lives, whose physical bodies
had completely deteriorated
from the weight of this kind of work.
And this is part of the hidden dimension
of what it means to also participate in these systems
and to use these systems certainly.
And I think of, you know, the water protectors also.
And, you know, this isn't just in South America
where people are fighting off large data centers,
but also Memphis and Austin,
and places right here in our own,
and of course we're in California,
a place that is so environmentally fragile.
I think it's important
that we at least kind of name,
and by we, I mean you, name
(audience laughs)
you know, tell us about the environmental cost.
- Yeah, so in order for Silicon Valley's type of scale,
at all costs, AI development to perpetuate.
McKinsey came out with a report recently
that projected that they have to build massive data centers,
and massive supercomputers,
to train the models on all of the data
that they're harvesting from people.
And then to actually host the model
so that when you're chatting with ChatGPT,
the model has to exist somewhere in like a physical space.
And the rate at which they are building these data centers
and supercomputers is historic, it's unprecedented.
And McKinsey's report said that in the next five years,
if we keep up the current pace
and actually build out what these companies are saying
they will build by 2030,
we would need two to six times
the amount of energy consumed in California
to be added to the global grid.
And most of that will come from fossil fuels
because these data centers and supercomputers
have to run 24/7.
And Business Insider came out with this investigation
where they found that utilities across the US are, quote,
"torpedoing" their renewable energy goals
in order to sustain the amount of energy
that needs to be generated for these data centers.
And I wanna make clear, once again,
the scale that we're talking about
is completely different
than previous internet era companies.
So during the social media era,
we also needed data centers,
but the rate at which data centers were being built
was roughly equal to the rate
at which energy efficiency improvements
were being made on these data centers.
So in the last decade, the US energy demand has flatlined.
And in the EU, the energy demand was going down
even as there were more data centers being built.
We are now at a point where the data centers
are being built so quickly
that we are seeing a historic uptick in energy demand
around the world and in the US.
And so we are literally single-handedly reversing
the climate progress that we made in the last decade
because of this technology.
And on top of that, you then have to deal
with things like public health crises.
It's exacerbating the air pollution
that is going primarily into working class communities.
There's been phenomenal reporting on Grok,
Elon Musk's company, that is training
on a supercomputer in Memphis, Tennessee,
predominantly Black and brown working class communities
that are now being pummeled by the air pollution
coming out of 35 unlicensed methane gas turbines
that are powering the supercomputer.
And they're now fighting tooth and nail
because they never even had an opportunity to say,
"We don't want this supercomputer."
It just arrived one day.
And then they started,
like people who had had chronic asthma
because this is a community that's already suffered
in an inability to access
their right to clean air for a long time,
they started coughing and smelling gas,
and being like, "What is going on,"
and then suddenly discovered this giant
hulking Silicon apparatus that had landed in their midst.
And now they're like going to city council,
fighting with their government,
being like, "Why did you not even ask us about this?"
And city government is now over their heads
because they didn't realize
that the supercomputer would come
with these 35 unlicensed gas turbines.
And they didn't know that Elon Musk would just,
well, that Elon Musk
would just buck environmental regulation,
just totally ignore it to set this up.
Then there's the public water crisis
that comes with building these data centers.
So one thing people don't often know
is that these data centers are most often pooled with water.
You can cool them with energy
by running giant AC units basically in these facilities,
but that is way more energy intensive.
And so the best way to do it is cool it with water.
But if it's cooled with water, it has to be freshwater.
It cannot be any other type of water
because that would lead to the corrosion of the equipment
or bacterial growth.
And so Bloomberg had an investigation
that found that two-thirds of the data centers being built
to support the AI industry now are going into communities
that do not have enough freshwater
for the human population there.
That includes California, that includes Arizona,
where this southwestern United States
has faced a historic drought,
the worst drought in a thousand years,
while it has also become
the second largest data center hub in the US,
potentially the world.
And if you go further afield,
I went to Uruguay to meet with a community there
that was also fighting data center development there.
And they were facing historic drought
that was so bad that the Montevideo government
started mixing saltwater
into the public drinking water supply
because there was not enough water to service people's taps.
And for people who could not pay for bottled water,
that is the water they were drinking.
And women were having higher rates of miscarriages,
people with chronic illnesses were having inflamed symptoms.
And it was in the middle of that,
when these people were already fighting
for access to life-sustaining resources
that Google was like,
"We want your life-sustaining resources
to cool our data center."
- Karen, I think about your work and your voice
as a light in the complete darkness.
Like, we're sitting here in the heart of Silicon Valley
and the weight,
I can just feel the weight
of the AI hype cycle that is around us.
It was on the escalator, if you saw that coming up.
There's like some escalators taking you to AI heaven.
I don't know what the onset-
(audience laughing)
It felt like it said something like that.
And yet, you know, I know we are talking
about large language models for the most part.
Our friend and colleague, Dr. Timnit Gebru,
and her incredible organization DAIR,
has been, and I know you've been looking
at other kinds of AI and, you know, you close the book
on a hopeful note,
and I'm gonna attempt to close this session
on a hopeful note.
Not guaranteeing that that will be the outcome.
(audience laughing)
But you've got all day to recover.
(audience continues laughing)
(audience member applauds)
You know, this idea of kind of like small task-based AI.
How could we think about AI,
AI, you know, is a big catchall for a lot of things,
but is there some promise,
and how do we disambiguate it
from the things you've talked about
that we know we don't want?
- Yeah, so I mentioned earlier
that there are a full range
of different types of AI technologies.
And I think really the best way
to think about the word AI is like the word transportation.
There's a whole lot of different transportation options.
You can have bicycles, rockets,
self-driving cars, gas-guzzling trucks.
And generally speaking,
we don't say we just need more transportation
to solve our problems, right?
We understand that we need to electrify our transportation,
we need to ride more bikes than fly more rockets.
Like, I really do think that the AI models
that are being produced by Silicon Valley
are kind of like the rocket equivalent in transportation
where, generally speaking,
there's actually a very narrow range of transportation needs
where we actually need the rocket.
And it would make utterly no sense
for us to give everyone a rocket to use for everything.
And suddenly you're commuting from LA
to Santa Clara on a rocket.
(audience laughing)
Yeah, like that's just not fit for purpose.
And I hope that we can move the conversation in AI
to start disentangling the nuances there as well.
But the thing that I write about
in my epilogue for the book
is about this story of this community in New Zealand
called Te Hiku Media.
It's one of the best stories that I've ever reported.
They're a Maori radio station
that really wanted to contribute to the revitalization
of the Te Reo Maori language
because, like many Indigenous peoples around the world,
Maori have almost lost their language
from racist assimilation policies during colonization.
And Te Hiku Media has been broadcasting
in the Te Reo Maori language for decades,
as one of the only organizations
that has that really long continuous history.
And so they thought we wanna bring this archival audio
to Te Reo Maori learners
so that they can hear the sounds of their ancestors
and actually reclaim their own language.
And so the problem was in order to do that
they wanted to create this interactive education tool
where they could transcribe the audio
so people could listen to the audio
while they saw the words coming up on the screen,
and then they could click on the words
and see the meaning, the translation,
see how it's used in other contexts
so that they can really learn this language.
But there weren't enough Te Reo Maori speakers
with sufficient fluency to actually do that transcription.
And so they thought, "We wanna use AI."
But they went about developing their AI tool
in a fundamentally different way.
First and foremost, they went to their community and asked,
"Do you want AI?"
The community said yes.
And then, with their consent,
they then taught the community,
"This is how AI usually works.
We're going to need your data.
We're going to need donations from you
of audio with transcription
so that we can train the speech recognition tool
that knows how to transcribe Te Reo Maori."
And the community was really excited
because they knew that it could actually benefit them
and not exacerbate historical inequities,
but actually reverse and give them back power.
And so they were more than happy to give their data.
And because there was so much buy-in and so much trust,
within like three days, they were able to gather enough data
to train a model.
And because this was a small task-specific AI system,
not an everything machine,
it was just doing one task really, really well,
they got away with just training
on a couple hundred hours of audio
and they were able to get to a high enough proficiency
that they could start transcribing their archive.
And then they went back to the community and said,
"Now that we have this tool,
how do you want us to use it?
What kind of educational tools do you want?
And what other AI tools do you want us to build with it?"
And another part was they promised the community,
"Now that we have your data,
we're going to be guardians of that data.
We're not gonna sell that data,
we're not gonna try to monetize that data.
We are going to create a legally binding license
so that if anyone ever wants access to this data,
they have to sign off on our community's values
to make sure that this data is never used
in a project that might ultimately come back to harm us."
And finally, my favorite part about this entire endeavor
was they used this as an opportunity
to also train the next generation
of Maori data scientists and AI developers.
Because they thought, "If we want to continue
having AI for our community built by us,
we need to train up the next generation
to continue knowing how to develop these tools
and knowing how to protect our data with Maori values."
And so, I mean, when you think about like,
that's what AI could be,
like, why aren't we all doing that?
And that's my vision for what AI
or how AI could really be truly democratic,
where it can really empower people,
it can really reverse all the historical inequities
and allow us to build fundamentally
a new sustainable and equitable future.
(Safiya and audience applauding)
- I hope everyone here will read "Empire of AI."
Don't read it at night, take it off in the morning.
(audience laughing)
Just saying.
No, read it, listen to it.
On Audible, it's actually amazing
listening to you narrate your book.
It's so, so powerful. - Thank you.
- You are, I think, the most important voice we need
to be listening to right now about LLMs and ChatGPT
and all of the attendant problems,
but also the possibilities and the solutions.
So I'm so grateful to have had this time with you.
Let's give Karen (indistinct).
(Safiya and audience applauding)
- Thank you.
(all applauding)
(audience applauding)
(audience cheering)
(audience continues applauding)
- Wow.
Are you energized? I couldn't tell.
- [Audience Member 4] No.
- No. Somebody says no.
All right, well, thank you so much.
(Jory laughs)
We've had a great morning together.
We wanna let you know that there is now a 30-minute break
that'll take place down in the Futures Hub.
Sessions will start back up at 11 a.m.
And please, join us back here at 2:30.
Don't worry about traffic or anything,
just come back here at 2:30.
We have a fantastic afternoon scheduled for you as well,
so please enjoy your break.
Thank you.
(audience applauding)
- [Audience Member 5] I'm gonna split.